Look, I think the system
is a combination of action
and inaction by the world's governments.
They usually say it's to help humanity,
society, the individual.
But the way things are going,
you can see that everything
the system does is against people,
especially against the poor.
Because they kind of push us
into being poor, on purpose.
Because what is a poor person?
A poor person is someone who doesn't
reach a certain means, a certain level.
But it's the system
that decides who gets there.
Because if it's about work,
there's no people that works harder
than African people. There isn't.
We work so much, so much, so much, only to
end up in a shack, in a self-built house.
Mind you, our house is good.
It's good because we
built Portugal's buildings:
the men from here build them.
Of course, for ourselves,
we build a good house.
But we work so much.
Human beings work so hard, they give
their blood to get the bare minimum.
People, this is inhumane.
What the system is doing
to people is inhumane.
And all they put in our heads is:
"Have hope for the future."
That future that never comes.
That better future never comes.
But it's the church, it's politics,
always: "Work, and God will provide.
Work, tomorrow will be better."
You work like a slave, and you never,
never have anything, nothing better.
And the most incredible thing
is that people think this is normal.
Human beings think life
is about work, work, work.
As a child, you don't have a childhood,
you don't do anything you like as a child.
You only do what you must.
When you're young,
you're already pushed into work.
As an adult, you have lots of things
to do, lots of responsibility.
They promise you'll live
comfortably when you're old.
With a pension that, in the end,
isn't even enough to pay
for the costs of old age.
Because we see it here in Portugal,
in Portugal, around the world:
old people are suffering,
because they worked their whole lives,
they reach old age
and the pension isn't enough for anything.
And if human beings don't
rise up against this system,
we'll go back to slavery again,
but a prettied-up slavery.
A beautiful slavery, like, because
when it's the government doing the shit,
it's all beautiful.
The name for slavery is democracy.
Like, they give something
horrible a beautiful name,
and we accept it as beautiful. But what's
happening in the world is inhumane.
What the system is doing
to people is inhumane,
because they push people into poverty.
From childhood, they put it in our heads.
And when we stand up
to rebel against poverty,
you see there's no way out.
Or, if there is a way out,
you need a lot of emotional support,
you have to be really well
prepared to get out of poverty.
Because it's programmed,
it's from childhood.
They make us poor and then they blame us.
They give us this feeling of guilt,
that we're the ones not doing anything,
but we're doing everything,
because we work.